<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" 
     xmlns:eg="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
     xmlns:egXML="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
     xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" 
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:lang="en" n="tei_clarin">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Parla-CLARIN: a TEI schema for corpora of parliamentary proceedings</title>
        <author>Tomaž Erjavec, tomaz.erjavec@ijs.si</author>
        <author>Andrej Pančur, andrej.pancur@inz.si</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>CLARIN</publisher>
        <date>2019</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>This file is freely available and you are hereby authorised to copy, modify, and redistribute it in any way without further reference or permissions.</p>
        </availability>
        <pubPlace>
          <ref target="https://github.com/clarin-eric/parla-clarin">https://github.com/clarin-eric/parla-clarin</ref>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Made from scratch.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Research Infrastructure for Language Resources and Tools <ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/">CLARIN</ref>.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-07-19">Tomaž Erjavec: more documentation.</change>
      <change when="2019-06-06">Tomaž Erjavec: adding some documentation.</change>
      <change when="2019-05-21">Tomaž Erjavec: first sketch.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <divGen type="toc"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="sec-intro">
        <head>Introduction</head>
	<p>Corpora of parliamentary proceedings are a quintessential resource for a wide
	range of research questions from a number of SSH disciplines, such as critical
	discourse analysis, history, as well as Sociolinguistics. Their most distinguishing
	characteristic is that they are (typically corrected) transcriptions of spoken
	language produced in controlled and regulated circumstances. They are also rich in
	invaluable (sociodemographic) metadata as well as easily available under the Freedom
	of Information Acts set in place to enable informed participation by the public and
	to improve effective functioning of democratic systems, making the datasets even more
	valuable.</p>
	
	<p>Given these reasons and the fact that parliamentary proceedings are often
	avaliable on-line, many researchers have already compiled corpora of parliamentary
	proceedings.  However, these corpora are encoded in a variety of different annotation
	schemes, limiting their interchange and re-use.</p>
	
	<p>In order to overcome this problem, the presented recommendation, called
	Parla-CLARIN, proposes a schema that can be used for encoding of parliamentary
	proceedings corpora (PPC), primarily for the purposes of scholarly investigations,
	and that could serve as a storage and interchange format for such corpora. This
	recommendations attempts to take into account the following aspects of PPC:
	<list>
	  <item>Structure: legislative periods, sessions, topics, speeches</item>
	  <item>Metadata: mandates, titles, parliamentary bodies, location, date
	  and time</item>
	  <item>Speakers: age, party membership, links to external resources</item>
	  <item>Political parties: name(s), history</item>
	  <item>Speeches: speaker, text, comments, verbal and non-verbal interruptions</item>
	  <item>Text versions: verbatim or redacted records</item>
	  <item>Multimedia: audio and video, facsimile of original</item>
	  <item>Linguistic annotation: PoS tagging, normalisation, syntax</item>
	  <item>Legislative aspects: specification of laws, roll-calls</item>
	</list>
	</p>
	
	<p>The recommendation is implemented as a parametrisation of the
	<ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html">TEI
	Guidelines</ref>, and XML-based recommendation for encoding texts for scholarly
	purposes. As oposed to most other such recommendations, the TEI Guidelines have the
	ambition to be applicable to texts in any natural language, of any date, in any
	literary genre or text type, without restriction on form or content. The TEI
	parametrisation proposed for Parla-CLARIN also allows a wide range of PPC to encoded,
	while making explicit recommendations on the manner of encoding various
	phenomena. The recommendation itself is formalised as a TEI ODD document, on the
	basis of which it is possible to derive an XML schema expressed either as a RelaxNG
	schema, a DTD or a W3C schema.</p>
	
	<p>The rest of these guidelines are structured as follows:
	the rest of this section details the scope, purpose and background of this recommendation;
	<ref target="#sec-general">Section 2</ref> gives the general requirements that a Parla-CLARIN PPC has to meet;
	<ref target="#sec-overall">Section 3</ref> explains the overall document structure of a Parla-CLARIN PPC;
	<ref target="#sec-metadata">Section 4</ref> concentrates on encoding the corpus metadata, such as information on speakers or political parties;
	<ref target="#sec-transcript">Section 5</ref> on encoding the transcripts;
	<ref target="#sec-multimedia">Section 6</ref> on multimedia information;
	<ref target="#sec-linguistic">Section 7</ref> on linguistic annotations;
	<ref target="#sec-rdf">Section 8</ref> sketches ways how the proposed Parla-CLARIN format can be linked with RDF; and
	<ref target="#sec-conversion">Section 9</ref> discusses conversions to and from the Parla-CLARIN format; and
	<ref target="#specification">Appendix A</ref> gives the formal specification of the Parla-CLARIN schema.</p>
	
	<div xml:id="sec-scope">
          <head>Scope and purpose of the recommendation</head>
	  <p>This recommendation consists of guidelines and a formal TEI and XML schema and
	  is intended for the encoding of corpora of parliamentary proceedings, regardless of
	  the langauge or country of origin, for the purposes of scholarly investigations, be
	  they from the field of linguistics, political science, history or other humanities
	  and social sciences disciplines. The recommendation is <emph>not</emph> meant as
	  the primary storage format of parliamentary proceedings, such as kept by
	  govermental offices, for which <ref target="sec-akoma">Akomo Ntoso</ref> is
	  preferred.</p>
	  
	  <p>In developing a schema for structuring of data, two approaches can be adopted: a
	  descriptive one, where as much as possible of the original data distinctions are
	  kept in the target encoding; or a perscriptive one, where the target encoding is
	  severly constrained, to enable seamless data interchange and esp. interoperability
	  with software tools. The Parla-CLARIN recommendation adopts the
	  <emph>descriptive</emph> approach, as the source data, time and effort devoted to
	  converting it, the intended applications, as well as country-specific rules of
	  parliamentary proceedings will differ considerably, and it is likely that any
	  perscriptive schema would soon turn out to be too restrictive. Nevertheless, the
	  recommendation does try to limit the plethora of encoding options otherwise
	  available in TEI to those that could be sensibly applied to corpora of
	  parliamentary proceedings, and where more than one option is available in TEI to
	  encode a given phenomenon, the text guidelines and the schema attempt to allow only
	  one option.</p>
	</div>
	
	<div xml:id="sec-back">
          <head>Background</head>
	  
	  <div xml:id="sec-clarin">
            <head>CLARIN and parliamentary proceedings</head>
	    
	    <p>The Parla-CLARIN proposal is developed as a project of the <ref
	    target="https://www.clarin.eu/">CLARIN</ref> European Research Infrastructure for
	    Language Resources and Technology. Before the begining of this development CLARIN
	    had already organised a number of initatives and events that deal with
	    parliamentary corpora:
	    <list>
	      <item>CLARIN-PLUS cross-disciplinary workshop
	      <ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/event/2017/clarin-plus-workshop-working-parliamentary-records">Working with parliamentary records</ref>, Sofia 2017</item>
	      <item>CLARIN Resource Families <ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/resource-families/parliamentary-corpora">Parliamentary corpora</ref>, 2018-2019</item>
	      <item><ref target="http://lrec-conf.org/workshops/lrec2018/W2/index.html">ParlaCLARIN workshop</ref> at LREC 2018</item>
	      <item><ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/event/2018/clarin-annual-conference-2018-pisa-italy">CLARIN Annual Conference</ref>, Pisa 2018: Work on proposal for COST Action Parlant: "Parliamentary Data and Language Technology" (proposers Maciej Ogrodniczuk, Petya Osenova)</item>
  	    </list>
	    At these events it became clear that existing
	    parliamentary corpora are encoded in many different way,
	    presenting a barrier to their interchange. Therefore the
	    CLARIN Interoperability Committee organised a focused
	    <q><ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/blog/clarin-parlaformat-workshop">CLARIN
	    ParlaFormat</ref></q> workshop (May 23-24, 2019,
	    Amersfoort) with selected participants at which the idea
	    of the present recommendation was introduced, the
	    participants presented their own experiences with encoding
	    parliamentary corpora and their comments to the draft
	    proposal, and the authors of the proposal gave responses
	    to these comments. The details are given in the
	    <ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/event/2019/parlaformat-workshop">slides
	    of the workshop</ref>.
            </p>
	  </div>
	  
	  <div xml:id="sec-akoma">
            <head>Akoma Ntoso</head>
	    <p>While there are a large number of recommendations and
	    standards that could in principle be used to encode
	    parliamentary proceedings, the
	    <ref target="http://www.akomantoso.org/">Akoma Ntoso</ref>
	    standard stands out in that it was explicitly developed as
	    an XML format for encoding parliamentary proceedings, as well
	    as other legislative and judiciary documents.

	    Akoma Ntoso is a ...
	    <!-- Še zelo pomembna glede Akoma Ntoso (AKN): Sem vse skupaj še bolj natančno pogledal. Praktično je tako, da ima slednji "samo" dve večji pomankljivosti:
		 - manjkajočo jezikoslovno označevanje (o čemer sva že debatirala): se pravi, da bi bilo potrebno v teh primerih  uporabiti kaj drugega kot pa AKN;
		 - med udeleženci delavnice bo veliko politiologov, sociologov ipd., za katere so zelo pomembni metapodatki o govornikih; v tem pogledu pa je AKN zelo neroden za uporabo: te metapodatke je potrebno zapisovati v URI (potrebuješ tudi URI reslover), pri čemer ni nobene ontologije; sem zato našel primer, kjer v teh primerih priporočajo uporabo drugih shem kot pa AKN-->
	    </p>
	  </div>
	  <!-- RDF: https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1860 -->
	</div>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-general">
        <head>General requirements</head>
	<div xml:id="sec-chars">
          <head>Characters</head>
	  
	  <p>A Parla-CLARIN corpus should, in general, capture as much of the text and markup
	  from the source as possble, while the presence of graphical items or other elements
	  that could not or were not transcribed should be indicated by markup, in particular
	  with the use of <gi>gap</gi>.</p>
	  
	  <p>The corpus should be encoded in Unicode, using the UTF-8 character encoding, at
	  least for European languages.  In cases where the original contains characters
	  from the Unicode Private Use Area, these should be either given their closest
	  equivalents.<note>TEI also allows for preserving the original codepoint even for
	  PUA by using the <gi>g</gi> element, the use of which is further explained in the
	  <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/WD.html">Section
	  on Characters, Glyphs, and Writing Modes</ref> of the TEI Guidelines. However,
	  such characters will rarely if ever be used in PPCs, so the current Parla-CLARIN
	  proposal does not include the gaiji module which allows these elements - if they
	  are needed, then the Parla-CLARIN ODD needs to be changed.</note></p>
	  
	  <p>End-of-line hyphens can be removed, and the split words joined in order to
	  simplify linguistic processing. It is recommended that this practice is documented
	  in the TEI header of the corpus, in the <gi>hyphenation</gi> element.</p>
	  
	  <p>Two characters, esp. prevalent when the source documents are in Word, deserve
	  special mention:
	  
	  <list>
	    <item>Non-breaking pace (U+00A0), which prevents, with some applications,
	    collapsing consecutive white space characters into a single space. As Parla-CLARIN
	    is not interested in preserving the details of the layout, it is recommended
	    that this character is substituted by the regular space (U+0020).</item>
	    
	    <item>Soft hyphen (U+00AD), which indicates that a word can be hyphenated at
	    that point. These characters should be removed from the corpus, as they only
	    complicate further processing.</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>
	  
	  <p>While not required, it is sensible to also normalise sequences of whitespace
	  characters (such as tabulators, end-of-line characters and spaces) into a single
	  space or end-of-line character. Again, this simplifies further (esp. linguistic)
	  processing.</p>
	  
	</div>
	
	<div xml:id="sec-document">
          <head>Documenting the encoding process</head>
	  
	  <p>Difficult encoding situations that are not covered by the TEI Guidelines should
	  be documented in the <gi>editorialDecl</gi> of the corpus TEI header.
	  In particular, if the source texts has been changed (so, ommitting or normalising
	  figures, text, EOL hyphens, special characters, etc. as discussed above) this
	  practice should be documented in the <gi>correction</gi>, <gi>normalization</gi>,
	  and, as mentioned in the <gi>hyphenation</gi> elements of the editorial
	  declaration.</p>
	  
	</div>
	
	<div xml:id="sec-langs">
          <head>Languages</head>
	  <p>The language of an element's text content is in TEI, as in XML, signaled by the
	  value of its <att>xml:lang</att> attribute.  The Parla-CLARIN recommendation
	  requires that the root element of the corpus should have an <att>xml:lang</att>
	  attribute, and, furthermore, that each element that contains text is either marked
	  by this attribute, or one of its ancestors is. Note that if, going by the ancestor
	  axis, the values of two <att>xml:lang</att> are in conflict, the one closer to the
	  context node is relevant one.
	  </p>
	  
	  <p>The values of <att>xml:lang</att> should follow
	  <ref target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp47">BCP 47</ref>, cf. also
	  <q><ref target="https://www.w3.org/International/questions/qa-when-xmllang">xml:lang in
	  XML document schemas</ref></q>.</p>
	  
	  <p>It is good practice to document the languages used in the <gi>langUsage</gi>
	  element of the TEI header.</p>
	  
	  <p>Apart from the above considerations, a related question is where to draw the
	  line between the object and meta languages, i.e. the language of the corpus and
	  the language of the mark-up. The TEI defines the names of the elements and
	  attributes in English, and the language of the corpus will, of course, depend on
	  the country of the parliament. It is less straighforward to decide in which
	  language the names of the attribute values (such as the values of the
	  <att>type</att> attribute) should be. Parla-CLARIN recommends that these should
	  also be in English.</p>
	</div>
	
	<div xml:id="sec-temporal">
          <head>Temporal information</head>
	  <p>Parliamentary corpora can contain significant time-related information, e.g. the
	  date and time of a sitting, the start and end of an MP's affiliation to a
	  particular party, the dates of the begining and end of a policial party etc. In
	  general, such information in TEI is stored in the attributes of the pertinent
	  element, which take as as their values a date and possibly time, according to the
	  ISO 8601 Date and Time Formats, and specified in the <ref
	  target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/">XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second
	  Edition</ref>. TEI offers a very rich set of attributes and anciliary elements to
	  specify time-related information, which are discussed in the <ref
	  target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#CONADA">Section
	  on Dates and Times</ref> in the TEI Guidelines.</p>

	  <p>Parla-CLARIN users are free to use any of the TEI temporal attributes and
	  elements, however, for most purposes, the following five attributes will suffice:
	  <list>
	    <item><att>when</att>: when a certain event happened:</item>
	    <item><att>from</att>, <att>to</att>: the start and end of an event or state;</item>
	    <item><att>notBefore</att>, <att>notAfter</att>: the earliest and latest known
	    time that where an event or state took place, used in cases where the exact time
	    is not known.</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>
	</div>
	
	<div xml:id="sec-idents">
          <head>Identifiers and referencing</head>
	  <p>In order to simply refer to elements of a TEI document (i.e. a Parla-CLARIN
	  corpus), these are given an <att>xml:id</att> attribute, as defined by <ref
	  target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-id/">W3C</ref>.</p>
	  
	  <p>Parla-CLARIN requires an <att>xml:id</att> attribute on the root element of
	  each corpus file, which should, furthermore, be identical to the filename (modulo
	  the file extension).  Parla-CLARIN also recommends that the divisions of the
	  document (element <gi>div</gi>) should also be given identifiers. While any
	  element can be given an <att>xml:id</att>, this is in general, not a good idea;
	  rather, only those elements that will or could be referenced should be marked with
	  this attribute.</p>
	  
	  <p>TEI offers a number of attributes that contain (URI) pointers.  Where the
	  reference is to an element inside the document, the value of the <att>xml:id</att>
	  being referred to should be preceded by a hash (#), as mandated by the XML
	  standard. However, TEI also offers another way of pointing, which can be used to
	  shorten otherwise long URI references, and this is defined by the
	  <gi>listPrefixDef</gi> element in the TEI header.</p>
	</div>
	
	<div xml:id="sec-files">
	  <head>Files</head>
	  <p>While this recommendation makes the assumption that a complete corpus is one
	  TEI XML document, this does not mean that it should also be stored in one file, as
	  the file structure is distinct from the concept of XML documents. To enable one
	  XML document to be composed of several files, the <ref
	  target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xinclude/">XInclude</ref> recommendation should be
	  used.</p>
	  
	  <p>As mentioned, we recommend that the file has the same name as the value of the
	  <att>xml:id</att> attribute of the root element of the file. This e.g. guarantees
	  that each file of the corpus has a unique name.</p>
	</div>
	
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-overall">
	<head>Overall document structure</head>
	
	<div>
          <head>Corpus structure</head>
	  
	  <p>As illustrated below, a CLARIN-Parla corpus should be rooted in an
	  <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element, which should also contain the <att>xml:lang</att>
	  attribute with the appropriate language code<note>For multilingual documents
	  (excluding cases where only a minor part of the text is in another language), this
	  code would be <q>mul</q> for <q>multiple languages</q></note>. The
	  <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the corpus then contains the metadata for the complete
	  corpus, including the metadata that is referred to by the subordinate <gi>TEI</gi>
	  elements, such as the defined taxonomies and the list of speakers.</p>
	  
	  <p>We do not specify what an individual <gi>TEI</gi> element should contain, as
	  the size and granularity of parliamentary proceedings corpora, not to mention the
	  national rules of structuring the workings of the parliament will differ
	  substantially. Typically, however, and individual <gi>TEI</gi> element would
	  contain one sitting or session or one day, in any case such data that has common
	  metadata that distinguishes it from the other <gi>TEI</gi> elements in the
	  corpus.</p>
	  
	  <p>Finally, although not given in the Figure below, a <gi>text</gi> element can
	  contain, apart from the <gi>body</gi> also a <gi>front</gi> element before it
	  and/or a <gi>back</gi> element after it. While the <gi>body</gi> will contain the
	  speeches and is obligatory, the former can contain preamble text, and the latter
	  various appendices or texts that are related to the speeches.</p>
	  
	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-docstructure">
	    <teiCorpus xml:lang="xx">
              <teiHeader>
		<!-- Common corpus metadata -->
	      </teiHeader>
              <TEI xml:id="id.1">
		<teiHeader>
		  <!-- Document metadata -->
		</teiHeader>
		<text>
                  <body>
		    <!-- Document text -->
		  </body>
		</text>
	      </TEI>
	      <!-- More TEI elements here -->
	    </teiCorpus>
	  </egXML>
	</div>
	
	<div>
          <head>Text divisions</head>
	  
	  <p>In the text <gi>body</gi>, as well as in the <gi>front</gi> and <gi>back</gi>
	  matter, the element that further organises the content is the division,
	  <gi>div</gi>, and each of the three <gi>text</gi> elements (if present) should
	  contain at least one division.</p>
	  
	  <p>The divisions can be nested, and are further specified by their <att>type</att>
	  and, possibly, <att>subtype</att> attributes. For the recommended values of
	  <att>type</att> we take as our model the structure elements as defined by Akoma
	  Ntoso. The <att>subtype</att> attribute is to be used for cases where some facets
	  of structures in the source data cannot be otherwise retained in the Parla-CLARIN
	  encoding, i.e. it is used when we do not want to lose some information about the
	  source data structures.</p>
	  
	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-divstructure">
            <body>
	      <div type="bla">
		<head>Title of bla</head>
		<div type="bla" subtype="foo">
		</div>
	      </div>
            </body>
	  </egXML>
	</div>
	
      </div>

      <div xml:id="sec-metadata">
	<head>Corpus metadata</head>
	<p>TEI allows significant metadata to be added to a document.  The metadata is
	contained in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element, which in corpora can appear at two
	levels:
	<list>
	  <item>the overall corpus teiHeader;</item>
	  <item>the teiHeader of the individual corpus texts, i.e. the <gi>TEI</gi> element.</item>
	</list>
	It is recommended that the metadata that is common to the whole corpus is stored in
	the corpus TEI header, whereas the text-specific metadata is in the corpus text TEI
	header.</p>
	
	<p>It is outside the scope of this specification to give all the details of a
	<gi>teiHeader</gi> element, for this, the user is referred to the
	<ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html">Section on the
	TEI header</ref> of the TEI Guidelines, and, of course, to the example corpora that
	are part of the Parla-CLARIN Git repository. Here we do, however, give some examples
	and concentrate on the metadata that is esp. relevant to parliamentary proceedings
	corpora.</p>

	<div xml:id="sec-speakers">
	  <head>Speaker metadata</head>
	  <p>Unlike some other proposals, in particular Akoma Ntoso, this recommendation
	  assumes that speaker meta-data is also included in the corpus<note>Of course, this
	  does not meant that links with corpus-external URIs are not allowed.</note>, as
	  this allows the corpus to be stand-alone with all the relevant data necessary for
	  analysis already included in it.</p>
	  
	  <p>Information on speakers is given in the corpus TEI header, in particular in the
	  <gi>listPerson</gi> element, itself a part of the participant description,
	  i.e. the <gi>particDesc</gi> element.</p>

	  <p>A <gi>listPerson</gi> typically contains <gi>person</gi> elements, which give
	  information on an individual person, as the example below illustrates.
	  
	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-speakers">
            <person xml:id="KucanMilan1941">
              <persName>
                <surname>Kučan</surname>
                <forename>Milan</forename>
              </persName>
              <sex value="M">moški</sex>
              <birth when="1941-01-14">
                <placeName>Križevci v Prekmurju</placeName>
              </birth>
            </person>
	  </egXML>

	  Each <gi>person</gi> must have an <att>xml:id</att> attribute, so that it can be
	  referred to from the transcription. Apart from that, the only required element is
	  <gi>persName</gi>, giving the name of the person, which can be then decomposed
	  into the person surname(s) and forename(s) as well as giving more details on the
	  decomposition of their name, as explained in the <ref
	  target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html#NDPER">Section
	  on Personal Names</ref> in the TEI Guidelines.</p>

	  <p>As illustrated, further person metadata can contain the sex of the person and
	  their birth date and place. Further elements are the persons <gi>death</gi> date and
	  place, as wel as (time stamped) <gi>education</gi>, <gi>occupation</gi>, and
	  <gi>affiliation</gi>.</p>

	  <p>In the context of PPCs, the <gi>affiliation</gi> is especially important, as it
	  denotes the person's party membership. As this is not necessarily fixed, a
	  <gi>person</gi> can contain several <gi>affiliation</gi> elements, each one with
	  its temporal duration.  Furthermore, the affiliation should not contain (only)
	  directly the name of the party, but rather the link to the party's definition, as
	  explained in <ref target="#sec-party">Section on Party metadata</ref>. The example
	  below illustrates this encoding.
	  
	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-affiliation">
	    <person xml:id="JohnDoe1960">
              <persName>
                <surname>John</surname>
                <forename>Doe</forename>
              </persName>
              <affiliation ref="#party.SDZ"  from="1990-05-16" to="1991-05-08"/>
              <affiliation ref="#party.FLM"  from="1991-05-09" to="1993-05"/>
              <affiliation ref="#party.ZZZ"  from="1993-06-16"/>
	    </person>
	  </egXML>
	  </p>

	  <p>Persons can have futher attributes, and TEI offers various elements (typically
	  typed) to express them; they are introduced in the <ref
	  target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html#NDPERSEpc">Section
	  on Personal Characteristics</ref> in the TEI Guidelines. The two more general ones
	  are <gi>state</gi>, which contains the description of some status or quality
	  attributed to a person,(or organization) often at some specific time or for a
	  specific date range and <gi>trait</gi>, which differs from <gi>state</gi> that it is
	  independent of the volition or action of the holder and usually not at some specific
	  time or for a specific date range. The former could, for example, be used to encode
	  the fact that a PM was jailed for a given period of time, while the latter would
	  e.g. be used for the fact that a PM is handicaped.</p>

	  <p>It is often advantageous to refer to external knowledge sources about a person,
	  such as Wikipedia or VIAF. This is encoded using the <gi>idno</gi> element, whose
	  content is typically an URI, while the <att>type</att> attribute denotes the kind
	  of knowledge source referred to.
	  
	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-external">
            <person xml:id="Kucan_Milan1941">
              <persName>
                <surname>Kučan</surname>
                <forename>Milan</forename>
              </persName>
	      <idno type="wikimedia" xml:lang="sl">https://sl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan_Ku%C4%8Dan</idno>
	      <idno type="wikimedia" xml:lang="en">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan_Ku%C4%8Dan</idno>
	      <idno type="viaf">https://viaf.org/viaf/68121580/</idno>
            </person>
	  </egXML>
	  </p>
	</div>
	
	<div xml:id="sec-party">
	  <head>Party metadata</head>
	  <p>Information on political parties, as well as other groupings of people, such as
	  ministries, is contained in the <gi>listOrg</gi> element, which is, just as
	  <gi>listPerson</gi> element, contained in the <gi>particDesc</gi> element of the
	  corpus TEI header. The <ref
	  target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html#ND-org">Section
	  on Organizational Data</ref> of the TEI Guidelines gives the particulars on how to
	  encode data on organisatons, and an example of two <gi>org</gi> elemets is given
	  below.
	  
	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-parties">
            <org xml:id="pp.SDZ" role="political_party">
	      <event type="existence" from="1989-01-11" to="1991-10-13"/>
              <orgName full="yes" >Slovenska demokratična zveza</orgName>
              <orgName full="init">SDZ</orgName>
            </org>
            <org xml:id="pp.DS">
	      <event type="existence" from="1991-10-14" to="1994-03-12"/>
              <orgName full="yes" from="1991-10-14" to="1992-01-05">Demokratska stranka</orgName>
              <orgName full="init" from="1991-10-14" to="1992-01-05">DS</orgName>
              <orgName full="yes" from="1992-01-05" to="1994-03-12">Socialdemokratska stranka</orgName>
              <orgName full="init" from="1992-01-05" to="1994-03-12">SDS</orgName>
            </org>
	  </egXML>
	  <!-- Note that @full="init" is misused, at least according to the TEI definition -->
	  
	  As with persons, each organisation must contain an <att>xml:id</att> attribute, so
	  that <gi>person</gi> elements can refer to it. The fact that the organisation is a
	  political party is encoded in the <att>role</att> attribute, where the suggested
	  values are defined in the Parla-CLARIN schema. The name(s) of the party are given in
	  the <gi>orgName</gi> element, which also uses the <att>full</att> attribute to
	  distinguish betwen the full name of the part and the initials of the party. Parties
	  are also created and dissolved, and can also change their name.  The former is
	  indicated by the <gi>event</gi> element, which, in the example above, we have typed
	  as "existence" and where the dates of its existence are given in the <att>from</att>
	  and <att>to</att> attributes. The same attributes on the <gi>orgName</gi> elements
	  indicate the temporal duration of the parties names.<note>Note that there can exist a
	  date where both names are valid names of the party - it is up to the processing
	  software to make sense of this situation.</note></p>
	</div>

	<div xml:id="sec-relation">
	  <head>Relationships between people and parties</head>
	  
	  <p>It is also possible to encode relations between people and parties, e.g. kinship
	  between PMs, or the fact that one party is the successor of another one. For this
	  purpose, TEI defines the <gi>listRelation</gi> element explained in detail in
	  the <ref
	  target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html#NDPERSREL">Section
	  on Personal Relationships</ref> of the TEI Guidelines. This element can be contained
	  either by the <gi>listPerson</gi> or <gi>listOrg</gi> elements and, in turn, contains
	  the <gi>relation</gi> element that defines one relation. The example below shows a
	  relation between people.

	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-relatpers">
	    <relation name="parents" passive="#sbi243926" active="#sbi243926-0 #sbi243926-1"/>
	  </egXML>

	  The relation defines the relationship "parents" between the <att>active</att>
	  persons of this relationship (i.e. those defined in the <gi>person</gi> element
	  with the <att>xml:id</att> values of <code>sbi243926-0</code> and
	  <code>sbi243926-1</code>) and the <att>passive</att> person of this relationship
	  (i.e. the <gi>person</gi> element with the <att>xml:id</att> value of
	  <code>sbi243926</code>).</p>

	  <p>Relationships can also be mutual, e.g. in the case of spouses, as illustrated below
	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-relatmutual">
	    <relation name="spouse" mutual="#sbi243926 #sbi243929"/>
	  </egXML>
	  </p>

	  <p>Relationship can also exist between parties (i.e. organisations), for example the
	  fact that one party is a successor of another. This can be expressed as in the
	  example below.

	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-succparty">
	    <relation name="successor" passive="#pp.SDZ" active="#pp.DS"/>
	  </egXML>

	  Another exaples is of a coallition of parties, where the coallition is also encoded
	  as an organisation, while the <gi>relation</gi> gives the membership of the
	  individual parties in the coallition.
	  
	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-relatorg">
            <listOrg>
              <org xml:id="cl.DEMOS" role="coallition">
                <orgName full="init">DEMOS</orgName>
              </org>
              <listRelation>
                <relation type="members"
                          pasive="#cl.DEMOS"
			  active="#pp.SDZ #pp.SDSS #pp.SKD #pp.SKZ #pp.SOS #pp.ZS"/>
              </listRelation>
            </listOrg>
	  </egXML>
	  </p>
	</div>
      </div>

      <div xml:id="sec-transcript">
	<head>Transcriptions</head>
	
	<p>The transcriptions of the speeches are the central part of this recommendation.
	Here, the main distinction to be made is between the transcriptions of the
	utterances of the speakers against the commentary inserted by the transcriber, such
	as the titles of the divisions, results of voting, comments on what is happening in
	the chamber etc. The former will be encoded using the utterance element, <gi>u</gi>,
	defined by the
	<ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TS.html">TEI module for
	Transcriptions of Speech</ref>, which also defines a number of other useful
	elements. The latter are encoded using a variety of elements, such as <gi>head</gi>
	or <gi>note</gi>, and possibly others, as further discussed below. We first give an
	example of a rather straighforward start of a division:

	<!-- Do we / will we have a typology of notes as well? -->
	<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-relations">
          <div type="???">
            <head>REPUBLIKA SLOVENIJA DRŽAVNI ZBOR</head>
            <head type="session">nadaljevanje 39. seje</head>
            <note type="chairman">Sejo so vodili predsednik Državnega zbora dr. Milan Brglez
            in podpredsednika Primož Hainz ter Matjaž Nemec.</note>
            <note type="time">Seja se je začela ob 10.03.</note>
            <note type="speaker">PREDSEDNIK DR. MILAN BRGLEZ:</note>
            <u who="#SDZ7.BrglezMilan" ana="#chair">
              <seg xml:id="SDZ7-Redna-39-2018-03-27.seg1">Spoštovani kolegice poslanke in
              kolegi poslanci, gospe in gospodje!</seg>
              <seg xml:id="SDZ7-Redna-39-2018-03-27.seg2">Začenjam z nadaljevanjem 39. seje
              Državnega zbora.</seg>
	      ...
	    </u>
	    ...
	  </div>
	</egXML>

	The example starts with the division heading, saying that this is the National
	Assembly of the Republic of Slovenia, with the second heading specifying that this
	is the continuation of the 39th session. Next come three notes, first one specifying
	who chaired the session, the second when the session started and the third, who is
	the first speaker. It should be noted that these are not formal specifications,
	rather, they are simply parts of the transcript that have been wrapped in certain
	elements.</p>

	<p>After these preliminary notes comes the transcript of the speech proper, which,
	as mentionedm, is encoded using the <gi>u</gi> element. Its main attribute is
	<att>who</att>, giving the pointer to the definition of the speaker. The element can
	also have the <att>ana</att> attribute giving one or more pointers to a typology of
	types of speakers; in our case, it defines that the speaker is the chair of the
	session. The utterances can (but are not required) to be segmented using the generic
	TEI element for segments, <gi>seg</gi>, encoding the paragraphs of the source
	transcription.<note>The reason why the TEI element for paragraphs (<gi>p</gi>) is
	not used is that utterances, being essentially (transcriptions of) spoken text, do
	not allow for internal paragraphs, a concept pertinent to written text.</note></p>

	<p>If, in general, comments on the transcription are encoded using <gi>note</gi>,
	some such comments allow for more precise TEI elements to encode them.<note>Whether
	these specific elements will be used or simply encoded using notes, and, indeed,
	whether such notes are preserved in the Parla-CLARIN encoding at all, will depend on
	the needs and resources of each particular project.</note> In particular, the TEI
	module for Transcriptions of Speech (<q><ref
	target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TS.html#TSBA">Elements
	unique to spoken texts</ref></q>) defines the following elements that can correspond
	to various types of transcriber's comments:
	<list>
	  <item><gi>vocal</gi> marks any vocalized but not necessarily lexical phenomenon,
	  e.g. laughter, sounds of (dis)agreement from the benches etc.</item>
	  <item><gi>kinesic</gi> marks any communicative phenomenon, not necessarily
	  vocalized, for example a gesture, frown, etc.</item>
	  <item><gi>incident</gi> marks any phenomenon or occurrence, not necessarily
	  vocalized or communicative, for example incidental noises or other events
	  affecting communication.</item>
	</list>

	The artifical example below illustrates the use of these three elements.
	
	<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-incidents">
          <u who="#SDZ5.AhačičMonika">
	    Spoštovani kolegice poslanke!
	    <vocal who="#opposition"><desc>shouting</desc></vocal>
	    <kinesic who="#SDZ5.AhačičMonika"><desc>banging of the gavel</desc></kinesic>
	    <incident><desc>police storm the parliament</desc></incident>
	  </u>
	</egXML>
	</p>

	<p>A special case occurs when the <q>notes</q> of the transcription of a speaker state
	that another (possibly named) person interrupted the speaker and give the content of
	the interruption, and the main speaker continues with their speech, e.g. <q>I propose a
	no-deal Brexit. /Jeremy Corbyn shouts: Traitor!/ The reason for this is...</q>. While
	the interruption might be encoded as a <gi>note</gi>, it would better be encoded as a
	separate utterace, which brings with it the problem that nested utterances are not
	allowed, so the main utterance needs to be split into two (or more) pieces. The example
	below gives an illustration how this is realised.
	
	<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-splitu">
          <u who="#BorisJohnson" xml:id="GB001.8.3" next="#GB001.8.5">I propose a no-deal Brexit.</u>
          <u who="#JeremyCorbyn" xml:id="GB001.8.4">Traitor!</u>
          <u who="#BorisJohnson" xml:id="GB001.8.5" prev="#GB001.8.3">The reason for this is...</u>
	</egXML>
	
	As can be see, the split is indicated by the use of the <att>next</att> attribute on
	the first part of the split utterance, and, if so desired, by the <att>prev</att>
	attribute of the next part of the split utterace. Both attribute must contain a pointer
	to the next of previous part of the split utterance.<note>Note that, in general, the
	utterance can also be split in the middle of a sentence, which brings with it problems
	for automatic linguistic processing, as, ideally, the parts should be first joined, and
	only then processed.</note></p>
	
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-multimedia">
	<head>Multimedia</head>
	
	<p>Parliamentary corpora can also have data from other modalities associated with the transcripts.</p>
	
	<div>
          <head>Speech and video</head>
	  <p>The transcription can refer to and align with external audio and video data using the
	  <gi>timeline</gi> element.</p>
	</div>
	<div>
          <head>Facsimile</head>
	</div>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-linguistic">
	<head>Linguistic annotation</head>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-rdf">
	<head>Parla-CLARIN in RDF</head>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-conversion">
	<head>Conversions</head>
	<p>A TEI encoded document is, in general, not meant to be used directly by software programs, rather
	it serves as an interchange and storage format.
	Furthermore, most TEI documents are not "born TEI", but rather converted into TEI from
	some source format.
	In this section we discuss some up- and down-conversion scripts that have already been developed
	for transforming source formats into Parla-CLARIN and from Parla-CLARIN into formats immediatelly
	usable by software.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    
    <back>
      <div type="specification">
	<head>Formal specification</head>
	<schemaSpec ident="tei_clarin" start="TEI teiCorpus" docLang="en" prefix="tei_" xml:lang="en">
          <moduleRef key="tei" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="header" except="handNote typeNote scriptNote"/>
          <moduleRef key="core" except="binaryObject gb"/>
          <moduleRef key="textstructure"
		     include="TEI back body div front text docDate"/>
          <moduleRef key="corpus" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="transcr" except="am"/>
          <moduleRef key="spoken" except="broadcast"/>
          <moduleRef key="namesdates" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="linking" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="analysis" except="interp interpGrp"/>
          <moduleRef key="iso-fs"
		     except="alt altGrp bicond binary cond default fDecl fDescr fsConstraints fsDescr
			     fsdDecl fsdLink if iff then vDefault vLabel vMerge vNot vRange"/>
          <moduleRef key="gaiji" except=""/>

	  <elementSpec ident="div" module="textstructure" mode="change">
	    <constraintSpec scheme="schematron" ident="divtype">
	      <constraint>
	        <sch:rule context="tei:div[@type = $div.types.debate]">
	          <sch:assert test="not(parent::tei:div[@type = $div.types.debate])">
	            A text division of type <sch:value-of select="@type"/> should not occur inside div with type value <sch:value-of select="parent::tei:div/@type"/>.
	          </sch:assert>
	        </sch:rule>
	      </constraint>
	    </constraintSpec>
	    <attList>
	      <attDef ident="type" mode="replace" usage="rec">
	        <valList type="open">
	          <!-- debateSection -->
	          <valItem ident="debate">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">General purpose text division
	            for all parts of a parliamentary debates.  This is
	            markup for a generic structural container for all
	            other parts of a debates that are not explicitly
	            supported with the other values of this
	            attribute. It is a good practice to use the
	            @subtype attribute for additional content
	            classification.</desc>
	          </valItem>
		  <!-- Should this be rather called "speeches", as it can be one or more?
		       Otherwise people might get the mistaken impression that each speech must go in
		       a separate div. Of course, this is then a departure from AKN... -->
	          <valItem ident="speech">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">General purpose text division for one or more speeches that were not necessarily held in parliament</desc>
	          </valItem>
		  <!-- Below we constantly have "Parts of a debate", but
		       a) this is surely 1 part, not many, and
		       b) We actually don't define what a "debate" is!
		   -->
	          <valItem ident="address">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate relevant to addresses</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="adjournment">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing adjournment notices</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="administrationOfOath">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing the administration of an oath</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="communication">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing communications from the house</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="declarationOfVote">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate relevant to the declaration of votes</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="ministerialStatements">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing written statements by participants</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="nationalInterest">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing resolutions</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="noticesOfMotion">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate relevant to the notices of motions</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="oralStatements">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing oral statements by participants</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="papers">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate relevant to the display of papers</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="petitions">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate relevant to petitions</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="prayers">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing prayers</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="proceduralMotions">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate relevant to procedural motions</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="pointOfOrder">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate relevant to points of order</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="personalStatements">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing written statements by participants</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="questions">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate relevant to questions</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="resolutions">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing resolutions</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="rollCall">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing a roll call of individuals</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="writtenStatements">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Parts of a debate containing written statements by participants</desc>
	          </valItem>
	        </valList>
	      </attDef>
	    </attList>
	  </elementSpec>
	  
	  <elementSpec ident="note" mode="change" module="core">
	    <attList>
	      <attDef ident="type" mode="replace" usage="rec">
	        <valList type="open">
	          <!-- AKN -->
	          <valItem ident="narrative">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Description in the third person of events taking place in the meeting, e.g. "Mr X. takes the Chair".</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="summary">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Summaries of speeches that are individually not interesting, e.g. "Question put and agreed to".</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <!-- AKN and slovParl -->
	          <valItem ident="speaker">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Name, role and possible description of a person doing the speech</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="vote">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Outcome of a vote</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <!-- slovParl -->
	          <valItem ident="location">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">The location of the speaker, who was not on the podium</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="date">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Date of the session</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="president">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Chairman of a meeting</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="comment">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Comment of parliamentary reporter</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="time">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Date and time of the beginning and end of the debate</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="quorum">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">The presence of the members of parliament</desc>
	          </valItem>
	          <valItem ident="debate">
	            <desc xml:lang="en">Comments on the conduct of debates</desc>
	          </valItem>
	        </valList>
	      </attDef>
	    </attList>
	  </elementSpec>
	  
	  <!--elementSpec ident="u" module="spoken" mode="change">
	    <attList>
	      <attDef ident="xml:id" mode="replace" usage="req">
		<datatype><dataRef name="ID"/></datatype>
	      </attDef>
	    </attList>
	  </elementSpec-->
	  
	  <constraintSpec scheme="schematron" ident="parla-clarin.sch-variables">
	    <constraint>
	      <sch:pattern>
	        <sch:let name="div.types.debate" value="('address', 'adjournment', 'administrationOfOath', 'communication', 'declarationOfVote', 'ministerialStatements', 'nationalInterest', 'noticesOfMotion', 'oralStatements', 'papers', 'petitions', 'prayers', 'proceduralMotions', 'pointOfOrder', 'personalStatements', 'questions', 'resolutions', 'rollCall', 'writtenStatements')"/>
	      </sch:pattern>
	    </constraint>
	  </constraintSpec>
	  
	</schemaSpec> </div> </back> </text> </TEI>
